Illinois Home Missionary Society records, 1872-1911.
Congregational Library Archives
Illinois Home Missionary Society records, 1872-1911.
RG4997
Congregational Library Archives
1.44 Cubic Feet
(2 boxes)
The Illinois Home Missionary Society was founded in 1871 at the annual meeting of the Congregational General Association of Illinois and was incorporated in 1873. The Society first existed under the auspices of the American Home Missionary Society and shared its mission to aid the spread of Christianity throughout the states and territories by organizing churches and commissioning ministers for congregations that lacked the financial resources to supply their own. The Society records series includes multiple items about the Illinois Home Missionary Society. This includes meeting minutes for the executive committee and the board of directors, various constitutions, missionary commission records, financials, scrapbooks, membership roster, and records detailing the merge with the Congregational Conference of Illinois.
Illinois Home Missionary Society
Roy, J. E. (Joseph Edwin), 1827-1908
Bascom, Flavel, 1804-1890
Sturtevant, J. M. (Julian Monson), 1834-1921
Restrictions on Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials were donated to the Congregational Library & Archives by the Chicago Theological Seminary in 2011; 2011-35.
Historical Note
The Illinois Home Missionary Society was founded in 1871 at the annual meeting of the Congregational General Association of Illinois and was incorporated in 1873. The Society existed under the auspices of the American Home Missionary Society and shared its mission to aid the spread of Christianity throughout the states and territories by organizing churches and commissioning ministers for congregations that lacked the financial resources to supply their own. The American Home Missionary Society had been active in Illinois since 1826, and the founding of the Illinois Home Missionary Society was part of a larger push for greater financial and administrative independence for the state-level organizations.
In 1878, the Illinois Home Missionary Society underwent a major administrative reorganization, assuming auxiliary status under the national organization. This change allowed the Society to gain even greater control over its funds and policies and to become completely financially self-sufficient with excess funds passed on to the national organization. As a result of this reorganization, the 1873 corporation was dissolved in 1880 and the Society was reincorporated. Between 1878 and 1911, when it ceased to exist, the Illinois Home Missionary Society issued 1340 commissions.
On the advice of the national council, the Illinois Home Missionary Society turned over its operations to the Congregational Conference of Illinois in May 1911. Its assets and work were subsumed by the Conference, but there was little turnover in personnel, since the board of directors of the new organization retained most of the former members of the old Society's board.
Scope and Contents
The Society records series includes multiple items about the Illinois Home Missionary Society. This includes meeting minutes for the executive committee and the board of directors, various constitutions, missionary commission records, financials, scrapbooks, membership roster, and records detailing the merge with the Congregational Conference of Illinois.
Arrangement
This collection has two series, each arranged chronologically.
Series 1: Society records, 1872-1911.
Series 2: Scrapbooks, 1878-1909.
Related Materials
Additional records related to the Illinois Home Missionary Society can be found in the Congregational Home Missionary Society reports, 1827-1891, RG0773, and the Congregational Home Missionary Society reports, 1892-1916, RG0774, and the American Home Missionary Society papers, 1816-1894, RG4675. RG4675 are microfilm copies of the Amistad Research Center's collection on the American Home Missionary Society records, 1816-1907.
Bibliography
Records of the meetings of the directors of the Illinois Home Missionary Society, in the Illinois Home Missionary Society records, 1872-1911, RG4997. The Congregational Library & Archives, Boston, MA.
Missionary societies.; Congregational churches -- Illinois -- History.; Scrapbooks -- Church history.; Church finance.; Constitutions.; Church membership.; Corporate minutes.; Illinois Home Missionary Society; American Home Missionary Society; General Association of Illinois; Congregational Home Missionary Society
- Society records, 1872 1906; 1872-1911; 6 Items
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains records related to the Illinois Missionary Society and includes meeting minutes for the executive committee and the board of directors, various constitutions, missionary commission records, financials, membership roster, and records detailing the merge with the Congregational Conference of Illinois.
  - Records of the meetings of the board of directors of the Illinois Home Missionary Society, 1872 1878; 1872-1878 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Illinois Home Missionary Society records of commissions, 1877 1911; 1877-1911 (Box 1, Volume 3)
  - Records of executive committee of the Illinois Home Missionary Society, 1878-05-29 1897-06-14; May 29, 1878 - June 14, 1897 (Box 1, Volume 4)
  - Life members of the Illinois Home Missionary Society Auxiliary to the American Home Missionary Society, 1878 1903; 1878-1903 (Box 1, Volume 1)
  - Records of the meetings of the directors of the Illinois Home Missionary Society, 1897-07-12 1911-05-17; July 12, 1897 - May 17, 1911 (Box 1, Volume 5)
  - Illinois Home Missionary Society journal, 1904-04 1906-03; April 1904 - March 1906 (Box 1, Volume 2)
- Scrapbooks, 1878 1909; 1878-1909; 3 Items
  This series contains scrapbooks related to the Illinois Home Missionary Society.
  - Scrapbook, 1878 1886; 1878-1886 (Box 2, Volume 1)
  - Scrapbook, 1885 1905; 1885-1905 (Box 2, Volume 2)
  - Scrapbook, 1898 1909; 1898-1909 (Box 1, Volume 6)